<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An impartial account of Richard Duke of York's treasons, and the several arts and methods made use of by him for the obtaining the crown of England to which is added The true picture of a popish successor, exactly drawn by the reigns of Christian the Second, and Sygismond, King of Sweden, and Ferdinand the Second, King of Bohemia.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46075</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13065047</idno>
  <idno type="VID">97050</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240849844</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I64</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R600</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13065047</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46075)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 742:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An impartial account of Richard Duke of York's treasons, and the several arts and methods made use of by him for the obtaining the crown of England to which is added The true picture of a popish successor, exactly drawn by the reigns of Christian the Second, and Sygismond, King of Sweden, and Ferdinand the Second, King of Bohemia.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Allen Banks,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Richard, --  Duke of York, 1411-1460.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Ferdinand --  II, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1578-1637.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Sigismund --  III, --  King of Poland and Sweden, 1566-1632.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Christian --  II, --  King of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden, 1481-1559.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97050:1"/>
            <p>AN Impartial Account OF RICHARD DUKE of <hi>YORK'S</hi> TREASONS, And the several <hi>Arts and Methods</hi> Made use of by him for the Obtaining the Crown of England.</p>
            <p>To which is Added <hi>The True Picture</hi> OF A POPISH Successor, Exactly Drawn By the Reigns of <hi>Christian</hi> the Second, and <hi>Sygis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Second King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Allen Banks,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:97050:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97050:2"/>
            <head>An Impartial Account of <hi>RICHARD</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Treasons, And the Several Arts and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods made use of by him for the Obtaining the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>RIchard Plantagenet</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> finding King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth to be a peaceable Prince, entered into a Resolution to supplant him and seize on his Crown and Kingdom, <hi>which he was the more in, couraged to do in regard that pious Prince measuring others by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, was extream credulous to those whom he ought most to have suspected, and as incredulour to those who were most faithful to his Interest.</hi> The Method which he successfully made use of for the accompllshing his ends, were these following: <hi>First,</hi> He took great care to please the King, and wheadle him into a good opinion of all that he did, whereby he got him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to be employed in Offices of the greatest profit and trust. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He procured the promoting his own Creatures, and thereby linked them the more firmly to his interest, since their dependancy was upon him. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> He procured those Ministers of State, and other Noble-men that were most faithful and true to the King and his interest, to be suspected and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He took all opportunities to villifie the King as unfit and unworthy to Reign. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> By getting the King sometimes into his power, and yet forbearing to do him any injury; but on the seeming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, behaved himself towards him with the greatest seeming submission and Loyalty imaginable, whereby the King conceived so good an Opinion of him, that he would never believe any thing against him, <hi>For</hi> (said he) <hi>if it had been true, that he designed to Ʋsur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my Crown, he would never have neglected such fair opportunities as he hath had for the accomplishing thereof;</hi> when indeed the true reason why he neglected them, was not Love and Loyalty to the King, but hope thereby to win so much upon the King's goodness as to obtain a more favourable opportunity, wherein he might accomplish his Designs with more safety to himself, and less suspicion to those who would have opposed his Enterprize. The <hi>Sixth,</hi> And that which was most fatal to the King and his Interest, was his procuring himself to be sent as the King's High Commissioner or Vice-Roy of the Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whereby he so managed the Business, that he alienated the Hearts of the chief <hi>Irish</hi> from the Interest of his Majesty, to that of himself and Family.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, left the Kingdom to his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, in as flourishing a condition as ever it was in since it was a Kingdom; but <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth was an Infant when he came to the Crown, being Proclaimed King at Eight Months old, and brought from <hi>Windsor</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> to be shown in full Parliament, his Mothers Bosom was his Throne, and general Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of Joy serv'd as the pledge of future Obedience and Loyalty. The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97050:3"/>present Infancy, and the future mildness of <hi>Henry,</hi> gave occasion to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Plantagenet</hi> Duke of <hi>York;</hi> who had some pretences to the Crown to lay the Foundation whereupon to build his own greatness by the ruin of <hi>Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and the House of <hi>Lancaster;</hi> the progress of which Conspiracy we find related by the <hi>English</hi> Historians after this manner.</p>
            <p>In the year 1447 being the 25 year of the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, the Queen, the Marquess of <hi>Saff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lk,</hi> the Cardinal of <hi>Winchester,</hi> the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>York,</hi> with divers more about the King, resolved upon the death of the Duke of <hi>Glocester;</hi> who besides the nearness of his Relation to the King, was one of the most faithful Subjects, valiantest Commander, and wisest and discreetest Councellors, the King had about him; but he opposed the Pride and Ambition of the Queen, and other Favourites, and therefore he must be removed out of the way by an unworthy and undeserved death, thereby to procure to themselves the absolute command and guidance of the King; their first attempt was at the Council Table, where they vehemently accused him of many Crimes, highly agravated by malice and Rhetorick; of all which he acquitted himself with so much sincerity, that the Council looked upon it only as the effect of Envy, for he used such Arguments as not only proved his innocency, but also increased his reputation and honor, whereat they were the more inraged, and persevering, they could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their end; that way they procured a Parliament to be called at <hi>Berry</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> whether <hi>Glocester</hi> came with the rest of the Peers relying more upon his innocency, that by reason of his Enemies malice, he ought to have done. The first day of the Parliament passed over quietly, being spent in the accustomed Ceremonies. But the second day he was made a Prisoner by the Lord High Constable of <hi>England,</hi> his Servants were all taken from him, whereof Thirty two were imprisoned, and himself found dead in his Bed. Five of the Prisoners were examined and Condemned; but as they were led to Execution, they were set at liberty by the Marquess of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> who having attained his end by the death of their Master, brought them their Pardons, signed by the King; by one clause whereof it doth appear upon what pretence it was they committed this Murther, <hi>viz. You are one of the many Traitors who came in the Train of</hi> Humphrey <hi>Duke of</hi> Glocester <hi>to destroy the King.</hi> (But yet the Duke had no other Army to assist him, to destroy the King in the midst of his Court, and the face of the Parliament than his ordinary Attendance, which makes it not unlike the late business at <hi>Oxford;</hi> nor is it to be wondred at that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> should be charged with such an improbable Story, since the Duke of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> who was the King's Uncle, and had been his Protector, and was at present one of his chief Favourites and Councellors, could not escape the like malicious Charge.) The Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who saw that all those things redounded to the advantage of his Defigns, failed not the laying open to his Friends, and the Male-Contents in how bad a condition the Kingdom was in. The King weak and governed by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, and ruled by the advice and directions of the Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them that now was the time for them to set the Crown upon his Head. This advice, sounding in the ears of the People, who for many reasons desired nothing so much as a change, was easily embraced; nor did he find much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in drawing to himself Subjects of the most eminent condition, who that they might have followers, and preferments, were ready to uphold him.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97050:3"/>And Rortune as if she also had been in and Compiracy against the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enry</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aised a Rebellion in <hi>Ire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> whether the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>York</hi> is sent to appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it. But the King was un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>appy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> than in this for the Remedy was not only worse than the Diseast, but all the evil which was occasioned by this Rebellion, was not caused by the Malady; but occasioned by the Physician; for <hi>York</hi> having cuseted the Tumasts, won so much honour and friendship in that Kingdom, that for his sake they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sook the King to follow the House of <hi>York,</hi> to which they ever after passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately adhered. In the mean time, all things go to rack at home and abroad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Normandy,</hi> and almost all <hi>France,</hi> is lost, and the glory of <hi>England</hi> began every where to decline, which was chiefly occasioned by the Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s machinations; where-with-all great numbers being corrupted, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was thought on but home bred Rancour and inveterate malice against the opposite Party. This unsteady posture of Affairs was improved by <hi>York</hi>'s Creatures to the advantage of their Designs. People would do well, say they, to look into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and see how the wisdom and valour of the Duke of <hi>York</hi> hath Domesticated a savage People, and reduced the most stubborn and obstinate to Discipline and obedience; adding that <hi>England</hi> stood in need of such a King, who were to be sought out, if there were not such an one already known, and were to be chosen, were it not by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by the Laws due to him, so as if he were not priviledged by his lawful pretentions, his only vertues were sufficient to purchase him the Kingdom, affirming <hi>Henry</hi> was an Usurper, degenerate in worth, and so by nature incapable and unworthy of the Kingly Office. Adding, that as <hi>France</hi> had been lost by him, so <hi>England</hi> would run the danger of being so too, if his preservation were endeavoured. That the necessity of the times, and the danger the Common Wealth was in, required other resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that since advantage, and the Common-Wealths good, were join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, it would be injustice, injury and ruine to delay the providing for it. <hi>Adam Molleins</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> and Lord Privy Seal, being a man of integrity, and the Duke fearing he would oppose his designs, he procured him to be Assassinated by Fishermen at <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> to the end all men might imagine he was slain by the outragious commotion of that baser sort of people. But all these things tending more to the undoing than the doing of any thing, he resolved to begin his work, by putting his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures upon some bold and daring actions, that being precipitated into unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable crimes; and knowing they had gone too far to retract their fear of punishment might make them obstinate in their Errours, and despair of a Pardon, render them desperate in pushing forward his designs; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though embraced at first in favour to him, must now be prosecuted for their own safety.</p>
            <p>In order whereunto he first perswaded one <hi>Jack Cade</hi> to raise men in <hi>Kent,</hi> wherewith he set upon the City of <hi>London,</hi> and did a great deal of mischief; but being routed, the Duke leaves <hi>Ireland,</hi> and goes to raise more men in <hi>Wales,</hi> wherewith he marched to wards <hi>London;</hi> whereof the King having intelligence, got a good Army together, intending to give him battel, but <hi>York</hi> shun'd it, hoping to encrease his numbers, and, like Fame; to gain by going; nor would he run the hazzard to try his passage through <hi>London,</hi> the denia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereof would lessen his repuration: but passing over the <hi>Thames</hi> at <hi>Kineston,</hi> he went into <hi>Kent,</hi> and pitcht his Camp a Mile from <hi>Dar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ford,</hi> ten or twelve Miles from <hi>London,</hi> and secur'd himself with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97050:4"/>Trenches and Artillery: The King brought his Camp thither likewise, and sent unto him the Bishops of <hi>Winchester</hi> and <hi>Ely,</hi> to know what had caused him to take up Arms; he answered, <hi>Nothing against the King or his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> but against some particular persons who were Enem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es to the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as well as to him;</hi> and naming the Duke of <hi>Somerset,</hi> he affirmed him to be the chief cause of his coming thither, promising, if <hi>Somerset</hi> might be put into safe Custody in order to his being tryed for such things, as should be proved against him, to dismiss his Troops, and present himself before the King, and serve him as all good and faithful Subjects ought to do. The Dukes end in this Enterprise was to justifie his own actions in the beginning, for to fight with the King at the very first would be scandalou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically opposite to his future Designs; and with this Answer he possest the King and the Nation, with a good opinion of him. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He thereby shun'd the danger he might sustain, if he should have hazarded a Battle and been worsted. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He doubted not, but if he could get <hi>Somerset</hi> se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, he should be able to accomplish his ruine, and thereby make the War more easie and plain for the bringing about his ambitious designs, which might then be accomplished by waies more mild and less subject to censure. The King on the other hand, who thought it would be somewhat hazardous to reduce him to obedience by force of Arms, seemed to gratifie his desire, and gave order for <hi>Somerset</hi>'s being secured; whereupon <hi>York</hi> according to his promise, dismissing his people presented himself before the King, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining against and accusing the pretended guilty person of Treason; and other high Misdemeanors; but <hi>Somerset</hi> who was not far of, hearing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self wounded in his Honour, could not contain himself, but coming from the place where he was concealed, not only answered to what was objected against him, but accused his accuser of High Treason, for having with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others conspired against the King's Life, and consulted how with least danger to themselves, they might bereave him of his Crown and Kingdom, an Accusation which ought not to have been so easily and slightly passed over, as it was to the utter ruin and destruction of the King. The King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>London,</hi> whither he was brought as a Prisoner, and presented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great Council assembled for this purpose at <hi>Westminster,</hi> where the two Dukes accusing each other reciprocally, nothing could be resolved of, for <hi>York</hi> denied all, nor were there any Witnesses to convince him, but <hi>Somerset</hi> perceiving the evils that were likely to ensue, if he did escape, did all that in him lay to have him put to the Rack; which in this case only was permitted by the Laws of <hi>England;</hi> affirming that <hi>York</hi> had long since resolved upon the ruine of the K. and the House of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> that he might make himself King and transplant the Crown into his own Family; but these Advertisements were of no force, his supposed ranocency defended him, since when he was armed with considerable Forces, he had presented himself unarmed before the King; which it is not likely he would have done, had he been guilty of those things whereof he was accused: Whereupon he was released, and retired into <hi>Wales</hi> to expect a more favourable opportunity: But coming again to <hi>London,</hi> he caused the Duke of <hi>Somerset</hi> to be arrested in the Queens Lodgings, and sent to the <hi>Tower;</hi> the King was at this time sick which encouraged him to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon this project. But so soon as <hi>Henry</hi> recovered his health, he not only restored him to his liberty, but made him chief Commander of <hi>Callairs;</hi> but <hi>York</hi> perceiving he had twice failed in his eadeavours to ruine him,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97050:4"/>went into <hi>Wales,</hi> where having got together a good Army, he Marched towards <hi>London,</hi> Accompanied by the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> the Lord <hi>Cobbam,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Warwick</hi> and <hi>Devonsh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</hi> and many others. The King Encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped himself at St. <hi>Albans,</hi> where the Duke presented himself to give him Battle; the King had in his Camp the Dukes of <hi>Somerse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Pembrook, Stafford, Northumberland, Dorset,</hi> and <hi>Wiltshine,</hi> with many Barons; and proceeding according to the Peaceable Instinct of his Nature, he sent some to the Duke of know of him why, he came in that Hostile manner, and what it was that would satisfie him, but the Messengers were hardly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rived when the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> at unawares set upon the Van-guard Royal, and Disordered it, before <hi>Somerset</hi> could Remedy it; so as all Forces on both sides giving Battle together, a Fierce and Cruel Fight begun, each side making good its Station, no man Recoiled, so many were Slain, that it was thought there would not be a man in all the Field left Alive. The Duke of <hi>York</hi> stood offering all Occurrences, and sent Fresh men to supply the place of such as were Wounded, whereby he made good the fight; which <hi>Somerset</hi> could not do, as not having so many men, and being more busie in Fighting than making Provision. The Royalists were almost all Slain, the chief whereof were the Dukes of <hi>Somerset</hi> and <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Wiltshine.</hi> The Duke of <hi>York</hi> having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Victory, and Slain the Duke of <hi>Somerset,</hi> who was the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended reason of his Commotion, imagined there was nothing left for him to do but to Assume the Crown, yet he thought it convenient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the people in their belief that he had taken up Arms only for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good: <hi>For having the King in his Hands, he resolved to make use of his Name,</hi> and Power to frame his Golden Age, and thereby arrive at <hi>His end by degrees,</hi> not imagining he should meet with any more opposition, although be found himself deceived. Some report that the King in this Juncture was but ill served by some Lords about him, and by his Domestick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whose Flight forced the King to forsake the Field, and greatly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the few that remained: The King had withdrawn himself to a poor man's house, where being found by <hi>York,</hi> he was with all appearing respect carried from thence and comforted, <hi>York</hi> assuring him that <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set</hi>'s death had established the Crown more firmly upon his Head; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving brought him to <hi>London,</hi> a Parliament was called, wherein <hi>York</hi> caused himself to be Created Protector of the Kingdom, whilst <hi>Henry</hi> King only in Name, was bereft of all Authority, and Safety, all that had dependency upon the King were put from the Council, and thrust from all Offices of Profit and Trust, both in City and Kingdom, and the Duke of <hi>Exeter</hi> was taken from <hi>Westminster</hi> and sent Prisoner to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omsret,</hi> a Sacriledge not formerly ventured on, The respect due to <hi>Henry</hi> was not yet so much diminished, nor his Majesty so much darkened, but that <hi>Henry</hi> the Young Duke of <hi>Somerset, Humphrey</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and other Lords that sided, with him, resolved no longer to endure the Injury that was done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and together with freeing their Soveraign to quit themselves of the eminent danger that hung over them: For every man saw <hi>Yorks,</hi> end, to be the Usurpation of the Crown, and that his delay proceeded from the fear of danger; or the King being by reason of his Sanctity Reverenced by the best, he thought he could not on a suddain compass his ends with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Scandal; and being Oppugned by the greatest part of the Kingdom, which would for the present Retard, and might for the future, ruin all his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97050:5"/>Designs. To effect which they consulted to call a great Council at <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> wherein it was resolved, that since the King was now no Child, and consequently needed not a Protector, nor was so void of Wit as to nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being governed by other mens Discretion; therefore the Duke of <hi>York</hi> should be understood as freed from his Protectorship: <hi>York</hi> could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himself from this Blow, being taken unprovided, and the thing is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> strengthened with such reasons as were not to be gain said without open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. The King being thus freed, called a Council at <hi>London,</hi> wherein having stated the condition the Kingdom was in, he shewed how that the Rent and Division at home had encouraged both the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> to Assault him at Home, and that therefore a Reconciliation was necessary; the which if particular mens Offences, and the Offences of his own Family were likely to hinder, he for his part would forget the Injuries done unto himself, and would endeavour the prevailing with his Courtiers to an agreement with those who had Spilt their Blood in the late Uproars, promising that the Duke of <hi>York</hi> and his followers should in this business have nothing to do but to desire, choice was made of some persons of Quality to be sent to the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and some of the House of <hi>Lancaster</hi> that had forborn com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Court since the Battle of St. <hi>Albans,</hi> who acquainted them severally that they were sent by the King to Treat with them about things necessary to the publick Peace, and their private Tranquillity: The Duke of <hi>York</hi> with the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> and others his partakers, came accompanied with 1500. men: The Duke of <hi>Somerset,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Clifford</hi> waited upon by as many, these were Sons to the three Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Slain in the aforesaid Battle, the Dukes of <hi>Buckingham</hi> and <hi>Exeter,</hi> and most of the Nobility of <hi>England</hi> that favoured the King and the House of <hi>Lancaster</hi> appeared in like manner; Lodgings were severally appointed for them in different places, to prevent their Encountring, the City was assigned to <hi>York</hi>'s Faction, and the Suburbs to that of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> the King and Queen Lodging at the Bishops House, served as a Bar between them; the Lord Mayor and Magistracy of <hi>London,</hi> together with 5000 Armed men supplied the place of Guard, walking the Streets day and night to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Tumults: Those of <hi>York</hi> Assembled themselves together at <hi>Black-Fryers,</hi> and those of <hi>Lancaster</hi> at <hi>Westminster,</hi> wherein the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> laboured much.</p>
            <p>At last a Reconciliation was Signed, wherein the Offenders being Fined in certain Fayments to the Offended, they all obliged themselves to the Obedience of the King, and to esteem those as Friends or Enemies whom the King should esteem such; which being done, a Solemn Procession was made, wherein all the Nobility of both Factions intermingled, did walk before the King in his Robes and Diadem, and the Duke of <hi>York</hi> followed after him, Leading the Queen by the Arm, but all this was but a bare shew and no real agreement, as appears by what some after fell out.</p>
            <p>This being over, the Duke went to <hi>York, Warwick</hi> staid in <hi>London,</hi> his charge of <hi>Calla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> detaining him longer at Court, during whose stay at Court, there happened a Quarrel between one of his men and one of the Kings Servants, and the Kings Servant being wounded, <hi>Warwick</hi>'s man Fled to the place of Safety, whereat the Kings Servants being Inraged, set upon the Earl as he came from Council, but being assisted by some, he leaped in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into his Boat and recovered the City, from whence he posted to <hi>York,</hi> and brought the first news hereof to the Duke himself, telling him that the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97050:5"/>last Fortuise of War was to be attempted; wherefore he presently went to <hi>Callais</hi> to seise himself of the Town; which if the King had prevented; as he might well have done, all their designs had been broken for, want of a place of retreat and Safety: The duke sent <hi>Warw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Father toward <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> with, such Troops as were in readiness to complain of the. Voolated Faith, and demanded Justice, to the end that if it should be demed, their Actions might appear more Justifiable; the Duke In the mean while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a good Army to follow him; the Earl Marched towards <hi>London,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Dukes command with about 5000 men, what the Queen ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertised of his coming, gave order to the Lord <hi>Audely</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> through, whose Territories he was to pass) to give him Battel; the Baron having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this Commission, met him near <hi>Drayton</hi> in <hi>Shropshire</hi> with 10000 Figh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g men. The Earl seeing himself Thwarred resolved to Fight, and Encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping himself near the Baron, there was only a small River parted the two Armies; he lay still all night, but upon break of day he commanded his Bow-men to shoot into the Royalist Camp, and then Retreat. <hi>Andely</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by the Arrows Egg'd by the Queens express command to take the Earl alive or dead, and encouraged by seeing him retire, which he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined was the effect of his Fear; he commanded his Vanguard to pass over the Water and stay him, himself passing over at the same time, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> those which remained behind were of no use unto him, which was the very thing the Earl aimed at in his Retreat, and having obtained his advantage, he suddenly turned about and Assaulted him with so much Fury, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently overthrew him, the Baron being one of the first that was Slain.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>York</hi> having received advertisement from the Earl himself of this good success, writ thereof to the Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> Governour of <hi>Callais,</hi> who presently comes to them, and brings from thence a good Band of Old Souldiers: The three Armies being United, <hi>York</hi> pitch'd his Camp near <hi>Ludlow</hi> upon the Confines of <hi>Wales,</hi> whether the King went likewise and planted his, but some of <hi>York</hi>'s Army forsaking him and flying to the Kings Camp, and he being afraid that others would do the like, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently fled towards <hi>Wales,</hi> from whence he went to <hi>Ireland;</hi> his E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>est Son the Earh of <hi>March</hi> with <hi>Warwick</hi> and his Father went to <hi>Jersey,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Callis;</hi> the King sent after them, but in vain, wherefore he ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished them, and by Parhament declared them to be Rebels and Traitors to himself, and Enemies to the Kingdom; he Confiscared them Goods and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposed of their Commands, giving the Wardenship of the <hi>North</hi> Marches to the Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and the Command of <hi>Callais</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Somerset.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was indeed the best and most likely way to have prevented their designs, and saved himself from being first Deposed and then Murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Had it been taken in time, but alas it was thought of too late, for the Duke of <hi>Somerset</hi> believing he should have obtained possession of <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> with as much ease as he had the grant to command it, went thither with a good Band of Souldiers, but he found the Cannon discharged from the Town against him as an Enemy, and notwithstanding he thewed them his Lettere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atents from the King, yet it availed him nothing; Nay his Ships that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to block them up, went into the Haven of <hi>Calldis,</hi> delivering those that commanded them into the Hands of the Earl of <hi>March,</hi> and they word forth with Beneaded. <hi>Somerset</hi>'s Army being wasted by Skirmishes, be sent to the King for Recruits, who sent unto him the Lord <hi>Rivers,</hi> and Sir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97050:6"/>Woodveil</hi> with about 400 men, who being come to <hi>Sandwich,</hi> the Winds proved so contrary that they could not put to Sea: <hi>The Duke of</hi> York's <hi>Creatures about the King gave notice of all these things to the Earl of</hi> March, who sent away Sir <hi>John Denham</hi> with a Compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Souldiers, more Valiant then Numorous; who with a Wind as Favourable to them as it was country to the Royalists, entred the Haven and Town of <hi>Santhrich;</hi> which being Unguarded and free from Suspition, he found most of the Inhabitants a Sleep, and took the Lord <hi>Rivers</hi> and his Son in their Beds, Sack'd several Houses, made himself Master of the Chiefest of the Kings Ships, furnished with all manner of Warlike Provisions, and returned to <hi>Callais,</hi> presenting the Ships and Prisoners to the Earl of <hi>March: Warwick</hi> made use of the Ships to Convey him into <hi>Ireland</hi> to the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to advise with him, who ordered that he and <hi>March</hi> should go for <hi>England,</hi> and vex the King till he could raise an Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and come and joyn with them: The King to prohibit their Landing, caused the Sea-ports to be Fortified, deputing Sir <hi>Simon Monford</hi> for that work, who to effect it went to get into <hi>Sandwich. But nothing being done in Court whereof the Earl of</hi> March <hi>had not notice given him by the Kings Domesticks, who were all or most of them the Duke of</hi> York<hi>'s Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and had devoted themselves to the Worship of the Rising Sun.</hi> He sent thither the Lord <hi>Falconbridge,</hi> who took it again the second time, and sent <hi>Monford</hi> and divers others, Prisoners to <hi>Callais, March</hi> and <hi>Warwick</hi> having caused <hi>Monford</hi>'s Head to be be struck off, and given Order what belonged to <hi>Callais,</hi> Landed in <hi>Kent,</hi> where they were met by the Lord <hi>Colham,</hi> with 4000. Fightingmen: The King being Informed hereof, gathered a good Army, with which he Marched to <hi>Northampton,</hi> whether <hi>March</hi> and <hi>Warwick</hi> came likewise, with an Army of 20000 men; and <hi>March</hi> Egged on by his Youth, <hi>And a desire to make himself Heir Apparent to the Crown, he being yet but Heir Presumptive at best.</hi> Upon <hi>July</hi> the 9th 1460. Early in the Morning begun the Battle, their Arrows played hard on both sides, whilest any were left, and then they came to Handy-Blows for five Hours together, without any difference; but at last the King was the loser, with the death of most of his Nobles, and 10000 Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; the loss was great, but might have been repaired, had he not lost himself, but being bereft of his Defenders who were Slain round about his person, he fell a Prey in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Enemies hands; the Queen, the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Somerset</hi> fled to the Bishoprick of <hi>Durham,</hi> and <hi>March</hi> returned Victorious, leading the King with him to <hi>London,</hi> where he Inflicted such punishments as are accustomed in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice of Civil Wars, upon such of his Opposers as he found in the City.</p>
            <p>Post after Post was sent into <hi>Ireland</hi> to acquaint the Duke with this Victory; so that persmading himself there remained nothing now to hinder his taking possession of the Crown, he left <hi>Ireland</hi> and came to <hi>London,</hi> at the same time when the Parliament was Assembled: He entred <hi>London</hi> accompanied with great Troops of men, the Trumpets Sounding, and the Sword carried before him as Kings use to have, only with this difference, it is usually carried Sheathed before them, but before him it was carried Naked: He Lighted off his Horse at the Kings Palace at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and entring into the upper House of Parliament, where the Kings Throne is, he laid his Hand a good while upon it, as if by that Act he had taken possession of it, and then turned to those that were by to see how they resented it; and as it is natural for most men to Flatter themselves into a belief of that which they Passionatly desire, so he thought they approved of his Action: But the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> standing up and asking him, <hi>If he would be pleased to go see the King,</hi> he changed Countenance and Angerly Answered, <hi>He knew not any in the Kingdom to whom he ow'd that Duty.</hi> Then he went forth, and entring into the Kings Lodgings, caused several Doors which he found sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to be broken open; after which he returned again to the Parliament-house, and fat himself down in the Kings Chair, under the Cloth of State, where after he had sat a while, he told them a long rabble of Reasons, why he had sat down in that place, <hi>Affirming that it most properly belonged unto him,</hi> &amp;c. When he had done speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lords were all so astonished (except those of his Party) that they stood as so many dumb immoveable Statues, no man opening his Mouth, whereat being not very well pleased, he wished them to think upon what he had said, then being again desired to go Visit the King, he Answered, <hi>God only excepted, he knew no Saperior.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97050:6"/>
            <p> The King finding himself so much over-reached and over marched by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was forced to give his Royal Assent to an Act of Parliament for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Eldest Son and Hen, and declaring the Duke of <hi>York</hi> Hen Apparent to the Crown.</p>
            <p>Proud Presumptive <hi>York</hi> would nothing less gratifie thy Ambition, and Satrate thy revenge, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the utter r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>une of the Son, the Eldest Son and Help of thy King and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign to was them no baser stuff to be found than Innocent Royal Blood, Where with to lay the foundation of thy Aspiring Hopes and future greatness? and must the Prince, a Prince Royally Born, whose Vertue and Valour gained him the Umversal Love and Admination of all men, except thy self, and those of thy Faction, fall a Vaction to thy Malice and Ragu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and was it not Injury enough to Illegitimate him to the Throne, but you must wheedle hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Royal Father, from whose Loyns he Sprung, to acquiesce in his ruine too; although thereby he was so far from securing his Life and estalishing his Throne, that he by that means opened a way and gave thee an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to deprive him of both?</p>
            <p>The Young Prince and the Queen hearing how things went at <hi>London,</hi> raised an Army in the <hi>North,</hi> consisting of 18000 men, among whom was most of the Lords of the <hi>Northern</hi> parts of <hi>England;</hi> with which Army she presented her self before <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels Castle</hi> near <hi>Wakefield,</hi> those about the Duke advised him to keep within the Castle, till the coming of the Earl of <hi>March,</hi> since she had no Artillery to Batter the Walls, but he Flush'd with his former Victories, Scorned to be shut up and be Besieged by a Woman: Whereupon the 31 of <hi>December</hi> 1460. he Sallied forth into the Field be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Hill whereon the Castle was Scituated to confront the Royalists: The Queen divided her Army into three parts, placing two of them in Ambush, and with the third she met him in the Plain; as soon as the Fight was begun he was invironed on all sides and defeated, himself and 2800 of his men being Slain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>March,</hi> and now Duke of <hi>York,</hi> received at <hi>Glocester</hi> the News of his Fathers Overthrow and Death, and resolved to be revenged of the Queen and Prince; but being Informed that the Earls of <hi>Pembroke</hi> and <hi>Crmond</hi> followed with a good Army, and were resolved to surprise him, he first went against them, and met them not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar from <hi>Hereford,</hi> where on <hi>Candlemass-day</hi> he gave them Battle and Defeated them; slaying 3800 of their men, after which he marched against the Queen, who had now gained another Victory over the <hi>Yorkists,</hi> wherein she recovered her Husband out of their Hands, this Victory was obtained by the Queen near St. <hi>Albans;</hi> but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of <hi>York</hi>'s approach, she retired <hi>Northward. Edward</hi> hereupon marches to <hi>London,</hi> where he causes himself to be proclaimed King, after which he marched against King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Army, and on <hi>Palm-Sundy</hi> the two Armies Ingaging, <hi>Henry</hi> lost the day, and upon the 28th of <hi>June</hi> 1461. <hi>Edward</hi> was Crowned at <hi>Westminster,</hi> shortly after which, he gave two other Overthrows to King <hi>Henry,</hi> the one at <hi>Hegely-More,</hi> and the other at <hi>Hexam,</hi> from the latter <hi>Henry</hi> escaped with much diffoulty, and fled into <hi>Scotland,</hi> but shortly after coming into <hi>England</hi> in Disguise, he was betrayed and taken sat at Dinner in <hi>Wadrington</hi> Hall, from whence he was conveyed to <hi>London</hi> with? his Legs bound to the Stirrups and there Arrested by the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the <hi>Tower:</hi> But after this <hi>Warwick</hi> taking disgust against <hi>Edward,</hi> set <hi>Henry</hi> at Liberty and forces <hi>Edward</hi> to fly the Kingdom, but having procured Aid from the Duke of <hi>Sungundy,</hi> he returns, and coming to <hi>London</hi> peateably, King <hi>Henry</hi> once more became Prisoner to <hi>York,</hi> who hearing of <hi>Warwick</hi>'s approach to <hi>London,</hi> draws forth, his Forces to meet him, taking <hi>Henry</hi> along with him, and on <hi>Easter-day</hi> in the morning, upon <hi>Gladmore</hi> near <hi>Barnet,</hi> he gave him Battle; the best of the day for a while being <hi>Warwick</hi>'s, but at length through the Darkness and Fogginess of the Air the Stars which were Imbroidered on the Earl of <hi>Oxford's</hi> mens Coats, who were in the left Wing of the Battle, was mistaken for the Sun which <hi>Edwards</hi> men wore; in which Error <hi>Warwick</hi>'s Battalion let flee at their own Fellows, who not knowing the cause of the Error, judged themselves bettayed, whereupon the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> with 8000 men presendy left the Field, whereby great <hi>Warwick</hi> was Overthrown and Slaind Some few Weeks after this, was the last and most Fatal Fight at <hi>Tewksbury</hi> between E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>ward</hi> and the Martial Queen <hi>Margaret</hi> on behalf of King <hi>Henry</hi> and Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>Exward</hi> his Son, the Defeat happen again the Queen, the Young Pritue fled, but was taken by Sir <hi>Richard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and presented to <hi>Edward,</hi> who having beheld him a while with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97050:7"/>in Austere Countenance, Demanded, <hi>How he durst with Banner Displayed, so presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously Disturb his Realm?</hi> To which the Heroick and Magnanimous Prince Resolutely Answered, <hi>That what he did was to recover his Fathers Kingdoms, and his own Rightful Inheritance; How did you dare then to presume, who are his Subject to Display thy Colours against him the Liege Lord and Sever aign.</hi> Which Answer so Inraged <hi>Edward,</hi> that he das<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> him on the Mouth with his Gantlet, and some of his Attendants most shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuller Murdered him at <hi>Edward's</hi> Feet. <hi>Edward</hi> having thus compleated his Victory, and being free from fear of new Troubles by the death of the Prince, and the Queens being in Custody, he comes in Triumph to <hi>London,</hi> and some few days after Harmless <hi>Henry</hi> followed the Fate of his Son, being Stabbed to the Heart in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and his Murdered Body on the <hi>Ascension</hi> said in an open Coffin, and conveyed to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church and exposed to publick view, where it rested one day, and begun to Bleed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>esh, from whence it was removed to <hi>Black Fryars-Church,</hi> where it did Blead as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and then he was Buried at <hi>Chertsey</hi> in <hi>Surry,</hi> but King <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh Translated it to his Chappel of <hi>Windsor.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The True Picture of a <hi>Popish Successor,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>ALthough a <hi>Popish Successor</hi> be the greatest Plague that any Nation can can possibly have befall them, yet such is the Ignorance of some, and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of others, that they endeavour the Alluring us to fall in Love with this Deformed and Monstrous Creature, whose Excellency and Beauty is in compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly describe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in an Excellent Discourse, called, <hi>The Character of a Popish Successor;</hi> And that Flood of Desolation and Misery which like an Inundation breaks in upon <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> as a Natural consequence of <hi>Popish Successors</hi> Reigns, which occasioned this publication, that the World may see what may be expected from what hath been done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christian</hi> the second King of <hi>Denmark</hi> laid claim to the Crown of <hi>Sweden,</hi> but the <hi>Swedes</hi> especially the Nobles) considering the Fatal consequence which would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary follow upon the admitting him to the Throne, opposed his Pretentions; and on the contrary he raising an Army, spent a whole year in the pursuit of his Title, but effected little, although the Archbishop <hi>Ʋpsal</hi> loving himself better than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth; took part with him, and very much promoted his Designs: But the Pious Archbishop quickly found out a way to help him, for the <hi>Swede</hi> rewarding his Treather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his own Native Country, by seising on his Temporalities; he exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Storming that he could not be Indempnified, therefore procures the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommunication against <hi>Steno</hi> the Governour of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and all his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers for invading the Rights of his Church and Bishoprick, whereby he encouraged <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to Invade <hi>Sweden</hi> once more; who accordingly sent a second Army under the Command of his General, who in a Battle overthrew the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and Wounded Sten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>our: Whereupon he was enforced to retire into <hi>Stockholme</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal City, and unto him repaired all those which intended to adventure their Lives in the defence of their Country.</p>
            <p>The rest of the <hi>Swedes</hi> hafely submitted to the <hi>Danish</hi> General, who thereby encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, marched to <hi>Stockholm,</hi> but finding many difficulties in his March; and when he came to the City finding no hope to draw them to a Treaty, and his Army very much washed he sent to <hi>Denmark</hi> for Reconits, and after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> while the King in Person comes to him, by which means <hi>Stockholm,</hi> was more closely Besieged, but yet held out brarely, so that the <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sh</hi> Army being wastedy and the Recruits which were coming out of <hi>Denmark</hi> being Wind bound, a Treaty of Peace is set on foot, and at last agreed upon by both Parties. But <hi>Christian</hi> thrending nothing less than to stand to it, pretends he could not come to <hi>Stockholm</hi> to finish the Treaty until Pled<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es were first given for the Safety of his Person: This the <hi>Swedes</hi> Assem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, and send him Pledges
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97050:7"/>of the Sons of the chief Nobility, who were sent Aboard his Ship; but <hi>Christian</hi> obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>Pope</hi>'s will to keep Promise no longer than until he could break it with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; he no sooner gets these Young Nobles into his Clutches, but he presently weigheth Anchor, and away he Sails for <hi>Denmark,</hi> and there Committed them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Safe Custody. Amongst these Young Nobles was the Renowned <hi>Gustavus;</hi> the Son of <hi>Ericus,</hi> a Noble <hi>Swedish</hi> Lord. Now in <hi>Stockholm</hi> Beleagured by the <hi>Danish</hi> Army, this <hi>Gustavus</hi> was of a Noble Family, whose Grandfather Married the Sister of <hi>Steno</hi> Governour of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whereby he became Inglasted into the Ancient See<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of the Kings of <hi>Sweden;</hi> in his Younger years he was Trained up in the Court under his Uncle <hi>Steno,</hi> who was no less Valiant in the Field, than Accomplished for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in time of Peace. Under him did the Famous <hi>Gustavus</hi> learn the Principles of War, which he began to practice under <hi>Suanto</hi> the next Governour: For in two Battles, in both which the <hi>Swedes</hi> were Victorious, <hi>Gustavus</hi> carried the Royal Standard of <hi>Sweden,</hi> being then but Eighteen years Old, and being now about the Age of Twenty six, he was with the rest of the Young Nobles delivered <hi>Christian</hi> as a Pledge, and being basely committed Prisoner to the Castle of <hi>Call</hi> in <hi>Jutland</hi> under the Custody of Sir <hi>Ericus Banner</hi> a Knight of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who kept him warily that he might suffer no wrong except from the Tyrant himself. This Imprisonment he patiently endured four years, but having dayly Intelligence of the <hi>Danes</hi> Cruelty to the <hi>Swedes</hi> his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men, he concluded his own condition to be like that of <hi>Ʋlisses</hi> in <hi>Polyphemus</hi> his Den, being reserved but as a chief Dish for the Tyrant's Palate, when all the rest were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; he resolved like a Generous Prince to free himself, and also his Country from Slavish bondage of the Bloody Tyrant. Having therefore upon a day obtained Liberty to Ride a Hunting, he followed another Game than what his Keeper allotted him, and fairly Rid away, having changed his Apparel as well as his Course, he passed through many unknown ways and eminent dangers; but after a Chase of three hundred Miles, he arrived safe at <hi>Lubeck,</hi> where we will leave him enjoying his Liberty, and his Keeper storming at the loss of his Prisoner, and endeavouring to perswade the <hi>Lubeckers</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliver him into his Custody again: And to trace the Bloody steps of our <hi>Popish Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor</hi> unto <hi>Stockholm,</hi> where we find him after four years returned unto <hi>Sweden</hi> with a great Army, wherewith he gave a second Overthrow unto the <hi>Swedes,</hi> wherein <hi>Steno</hi> the Governour was Slain; and then away he marches for <hi>Stockholm,</hi> but finding the City standing upon its Guard, under the Government of <hi>Christina</hi> the Wife of <hi>Steno,</hi> he endeavours partly by Force, but chiefly by Messages of Grace to get possession of that City, to which end he first confirmed a former agreement, which his General had made in the Field with the Lords of <hi>Sweden.</hi> And secondly he granted a General Pardon, and an Act of Oblivion for all former Faults. Thirdly, he sent seeming Commendations and fair Promises to the People in the Country, by the <hi>Swedish</hi> Lords that were of his party, yet in many places it met with very little respect.</p>
            <p>Whereupon they put on an Impudent Face and perswaded the People, <hi>Nay assured them upon their Honest Words, that</hi> Christian <hi>aimed at the Suppression of some only of the</hi> Swedish <hi>Nobility, such as Combine against him and his Government:</hi> But as for the people he was resolved to win them, and that they need not to want so long as Salt and Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings lasted: But yet withall they Threatned, that if they would not be prevailed with, speedily to submit themselves to the yoak, they should be all as Dead men, except they forsook their Country and fled. Whereby the poor <hi>Swedes</hi> were so deluded with his fair Promises, and Terrified and Affrighted with their Threanings, that they chose rather to be Slaves with quietness, than hazard the Displeasure of the Tyrant; yet the City of <hi>Stockholm</hi> stood out. <hi>Nevertheless, in continuance of time by the often droppings of his good Words, Serious Promises, Protestations, Execrations, Letters Patents, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations under his Hand and Seal, an entrance is made into the Hearts of the Credilous Citizens of</hi> Stockholm. The Gates at length are opened, and <hi>Christian</hi> admitted en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, and acknowledged by all for their Lawful King, although he quiedy declared himself to be a Lawful Tyrant; upon his being Crowned there were Solemn Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s held for all sorts of people, both <hi>Swedes, Danes</hi> and <hi>Germans.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97050:8"/>
            <p> This was a fair Morning, but a dismal Evening attended it at the Heels, for the King all this while was contriving the ruin of the <hi>Swedish</hi> Nobility, and was resolved since he had them all in one place within the Walls of <hi>Stockholm,</hi> and a sufficient Guard upon them, he would not lose the present opportunity, but would speedily dispatch them all; but it must be done forsooth under the fairest pretence imaginable, for the thing looked of it self with an ugly and ill-favoured face, even in the Tyrants own Eyes; and therefore at first, <hi>It is resolved, That a Treason should be Shammed upon them, and they should be charged with a Plot amongst the</hi> Swedes <hi>to Massacre the</hi> Danes; and therefore the <hi>Danes</hi> (as in their own defence) should Assassinate the <hi>Swedes;</hi> but, upon deliberate and mature consideration, this <hi>First</hi> contrivance was thought difficult and dangerous, and might in the event turn to the destruction of him and his <hi>Danes,</hi> being acted in so populous a City; and who knows what men in despair may do. Therefore <hi>another may was propounded,</hi> viz. <hi>that the King must look upon the</hi> Swedish <hi>Lords as under the Popes Curse and, Sentence of Excommunication; and to draw forth the Kings Justice with more colourable zeal, the pious Arch-bishop of</hi> Upsal, <hi>who had procured the Sentence, must open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuse the</hi> Swedes, <hi>as Excommunicated persons, for Treason against the King, Robbery of the Churches, and as spoilers of the Dignity and Estate of the Arch-bishop, and therefore he must dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Judgment against them.</hi> This device was highly approved of by the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant a and <hi>therefore to accomplish it; and the better to draw these</hi> Swedish <hi>Lords together, a Feast is appointed the third day after the Coronation, at which the</hi> Germans <hi>and the</hi> Danes <hi>likewise were prelent.</hi> And then the Arch-bishop before them all, steps forth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King and the whole Company, accuses the <hi>Swedish</hi> Lords of injury done by them to himself, both in Person and Estate; and demanded satisfaction for the damages.</p>
            <p>The Tyrant liked not the Charge, as not home enough, and therefore told him that he forgot the Pope his Sentence, the crime of Treason, and his own place, who ought in zeal to the Church, to have demanded punishment upon the offending per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; immediately he commanded his Guards to seize the <hi>Swedish</hi> Lords, and commit them unto safe Custody until the next day; and in the <hi>interim,</hi> he lets strait Guard up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all Avenues of the City, that none might be suffered to depart out of it; and the day being <hi>November</hi> 8. 152. not in a way of Legal Tryal, but in a way of Butchery, he Murthered in cold blood about a hundred of the Nobles and Chief men of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and Cirizens of <hi>Stockholm,</hi> and as soon as the Execution was over, he let loose his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers both upon the City and Country, all sorts of persons Ecclesiastical and Civil, Great, Mean, Men, Women and Children suffered all manner of violence and deaths, that Cruelty could devise; nay, their rage extended not only to the living, but to the Dead, towards whom they used all the opprobrious indignities imaginable.</p>
            <p>The lively Character whereof might be better described by some <hi>Dane</hi> that saw it, or some Lord Inquisitor or Popish Tormentor in <hi>Spain;</hi> or else some that were inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refled in the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Monster, or the <hi>Parisian</hi> Nuptials, or <hi>Irish</hi> Massacre, than by my Pen. After these horrid Murthers, Outrages, Covetousness began to ascend the Stage; and the King seized upon all the Estates both of the dead and living; and to make all sure, the Liberties of <hi>Sweden,</hi> being thus brought into the state of a dead man, he thought to bury them too, so as they might never rise again. To which end he set Guard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> all places, published Edicts, and did not only deprive the <hi>Sweeds</hi> of their Armour, but of their Arms and Legs; also saying in scorn, <hi>The</hi> Swedes <hi>could Plough their Ground well enough with one Arm, and a Wooden Legg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But pray observe the Reasons which he gives for his bloody Cruelty, and you will find his Conscience obliged him to it; for he tells you he was touched with much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion, and would not have done it, had not his Conscience tyed him to do it, in zeal to the Church, and obedience to the Pope's Sentence of Excommunication. And are we ignorant that the like Sentence of Excommunication hath been pronounced by the Pope not once, but frequently against all <hi>English</hi> Protestants, both Nobility and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, to yield obedience to him. But, it may be, you will say, that the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators of a Popish Successor, promise you great Priviledges under him; yet let us not be silly and foolish to believe what we can never reasonably expect to be performed; let us before we give any Credit to their promises, listen a little to the doleful Cries of the Survivers at <hi>Stockholm;</hi> the mournful Complaints of Orphans and Widdows, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97050:8"/>the dolorous Groans of so many brave Men of that Nation, suffering under the cruel Torments and indefatigable Butcheries of a Popish Successor; and let us there take a view of the abhorred Massacre of all sorts, Degrees and Sexes, contrary to all Faith, Promises, Oathes, Execrations and Engagements under Hand and Seal. But doth his cruel and barbarous Tragedies end here? No, they did not, for after this he sent Letters to all the Governours of his Garrisons, wherein he commanded them to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all <hi>Swedes</hi> that came within their Clutches, especially those of the Nobility, and these Tyrannical and bloody Decrees were executed in many of his Garrisons, and such was his insatiable thirst after blood, that designing to take a Royal Progress through all <hi>Sweden,</hi> he enjoyned by Proclamation Gibbets to be erected in all places, that so he might with the less trouble speedily execute all those which his Lust and Avarice account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unworthy to live; and the good old Arch-bishop of <hi>Ʋpsal,</hi> the old enemy of the <hi>Swedish</hi> Liberries, understanding that <hi>Gustavus</hi> was forming an Army to recover them, sent them a Letter, wherein he very piously beseeches them to be mindful of their duty to their Sovereign the King, and of the peace of the Kingdom of <hi>Sweden;</hi> with large promises of the King's Grace and favour to them, and of a safe conduct to <hi>Gustavus,</hi> if he would lay down his Arms; but <hi>Gustavus</hi> was better acquainted with the old Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Fox, than to trust either him, or the Tyrant his Master.</p>
            <p>But so soon as <hi>Christian</hi> had finished those Tragedies, he hastens with all the speed imaginable out of <hi>Sweden,</hi> possibly fearing lest the ground should open his mouth and swallow him up; or, lest the fame of his Cruelty should arrive before him at <hi>Denmark,</hi> and make that Nation abhor and vomit him out. But behold how Vengeance follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him: he is now King of three Kingdoms of the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea; and to secure <hi>Sweden</hi> he had left Guards in every place; but Cruelty never Conquers mens Spirits; a great Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant may be feared of all, but loved of none but his own Canibals; and a guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science alwaies pursues him, and suffers him to rest in quiet no where; And so it fell out with this King, for within three years he lost all his three Kingdoms, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing one drop of blood, or striking one blow for them: for as he left <hi>Sweden</hi> without one God-speed, so he came into <hi>Denmark</hi> without one welcom home, for he had so died himself in blood, that all were afraid of him, and looked upon him as a Monster; his Victory was abominated, his Person odious, and his Government grown intolerable, by reason of his Injustice in oppressing his own people, invading the Lives, Liberties and Estates of all sorts; and for his execrable Murther and perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness in <hi>Sweden,</hi> together with his distrusting his own Subjects, and relving upon Strangers, intending to bring them into the Government of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and so to Rule his Kingdoms in a Tyrannical way by force and rigour in a word they esteem him worse than <hi>Phalaris, Nero,</hi> or <hi>Sylla</hi> for having found a peaceable and plentiful Kingdom, he brought it into the most calamitous condition imaginable. By his Sacriledge, Impieties, Cruelties and Perfidiousness, whereby he provoked all men against him, especially the Duke of <hi>Holstein,</hi> who proclaimed War against him, and was invited by the Nobility into <hi>Jutland,</hi> where they all joyned with him; <hi>Christian</hi> now too late, although too soon for him, concluding the Duke would be made King, leaves his Throne and Country, providing for his safety elsewhere, and Shipping himself his Queen and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, with all the Treasure he could scrape together, he sailed into <hi>Germany,</hi> where we will leave him enjoying the just reward of his inhumane Tyranny.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Danish</hi> Historians observing that his Concubine or Whore, very much increased his and his Kingdoms misery: If any one should question the Truth of these Inhumane Tragedies, let them consult <hi>Saxo</hi> the <hi>Danish</hi> Historian, and they will find that there is not the Tythe of what was done by him.</p>
            <p>The Picture of a <hi>Popish Successor</hi> drawn by <hi>Sigismond</hi> King of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> who being declared King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> returned from his Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> and is Crowned at <hi>Ʋpsal</hi> King of <hi>Sweden, Francis Mallaspine</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ʋrben,</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Legare were earnest to Inaugurate the King after the Pontifician manner, hoping hereby to introduce the <hi>Romish</hi> Religion into that Kingdom again, but he was opposed by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>Addam Andracan</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Ʋpsal,</hi> who told the Legate that it was against the Custom and Laws of that Kingdom, for any except the Archbishop of <hi>Ʋpsal</hi> to set the Crown upon the Kings Head. <hi>Besides,</hi> say they, <hi>the King must Swear
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97050:9"/>to maintain the</hi> Augustine <hi>Confession exhibited to</hi> Charles <hi>the First sixty four years ago, and no other Religion in this Kingdom; but that which was established by</hi> Gustavus, <hi>and</hi> John <hi>the Third, the King's late Predecessors in the Parliament of</hi> Sweden. The King perceiving all the Assembly to be of that mind, he was content to receive that Inauguration from him. <hi>His Coronation Oath was given him by the Chancellor of</hi> Sweden, <hi>by which he promiseth to maintain Justice and Truth, to suppress Vice, to govern the Kingdom with Prince</hi> Charles <hi>and the</hi> Swedish <hi>Parliament, to admit no Strangers into his Councils, or chief Offices of his Kingdom; that he will lay no Tax upon the people, except he be necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereto by War, or Marriage of his Children, or Reparation of Decayed Castles; that he will maintain the Priviledges of the Nobility, Clergy and People, and their Peace and Welfare.</hi> Then in the Parliament some Laws were Enacted for the Governing the Kingdom in the King's Absence, and the next <hi>June</hi> after he returned to <hi>Poland:</hi> Here was an Oath Solemnly taken, but with as much intent to keep it, as the Wolves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to keep theirs made to the Sheep, when they promised to guard and secure them from danger; for the poor <hi>Swedes</hi> by woful experience found when he had gotten the Kingdom: He like a Jesuited Prince forgot, or rather wilfully refused to keep his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, for he Invades <hi>Sweden</hi> his Native Country with an Army of Strangers, to the great danger of undoing his Uncle <hi>Charles,</hi> with the Nobility Clergy and whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for which cause they being grieved, that his Majesty should so violate his Promises, and impiously break his Coronation Oath, were forced to renounce all Fealty, and Allegiance to him; yet such was their love to that Family, that they were content his Son should sit upon the Throne after him, if so be his Majesty will resolve within six months to send him thither to be instructed in the Protestant Faith under Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his Uncle and the other Peers of <hi>Sweden;</hi> But if the King refused to perform this within the prefixed time, they must disinherit him and his Posterity; therefore they beseech his Majesty not to slight the humble Petition of the Kingdom, nor the welfare of his Posterity: The six months prefixed for the King's Resolution being past, and no Answer from him, a Parliament is called, in which Prince <hi>Charles</hi> is desired to take the Kingdom, which he refused until other six Months were expired, wherein to expect the Young Prince to be sent thither to be Instructed in the Religion and and Laws of this Kingdom; which time being expired too, and no Answer coming from King <hi>Sigismond,</hi> he was Crowned King, and after him succeeded the Great <hi>Gustavus. Adolphus.</hi> And by this does eminently appear the usage that Protestants must expect under a <hi>Popish Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, the <hi>Bohemians</hi> having been long persecuted with Rage and Cruelty under the Government of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> were at last blessed with a calm, and the free exercise of the pure Religion, during the Reigns of three Kings successively, the last of which was <hi>Matthias;</hi> who coming to <hi>Bohemia Anno</hi> 1617. calls an Assembly of States, but being in time of Harvest there was but a thin appearance, however he acquainted those which came, that since he had no Issue he would adopt <hi>Ferdinand</hi> for his Son, highly commending his Vertues, and desiring he might be Crowned, the Answer of the Assembly was, that a business of so great consequence, could not be done in the absence of the <hi>Ʋnited Provinces;</hi> the King cryed, that what <hi>Bohemia</hi> did, would be confirmed by all the rest, the King also urged, that he grew Faint, and that it could not be deferred untill another time; the Assembly Answered that the term of receiving him for King was new, that he ought first to be chosen, and then received; and some perceiving there was no obtaining of free choice departed, others partly allured by Promises, and partly deterred by Threats, stayed and were present at the Coronation of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the second Emperor of <hi>Germany</hi> being thus obtruded upon the <hi>Bohemians</hi> for their King, contrary to the Ancient Constitutions and Customs of the Kingdom, and not lawfully Elected thereunto as he ought to have been, retired presently into <hi>Germany,</hi> and thereupon the <hi>Papists</hi> began to Crow, and openly to Threaten the <hi>Protestants;</hi> and it appeared sufficiently that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Swore to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with his Mouth, but in his Heart to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and presently after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the <hi>Popish</hi> Bishop Clergy and Nobles began to vex his Subjects for Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that assurance which the King had given to them. They attempted also the like in <hi>Prague,</hi> the Jesuits dayly Threatning that their Liberty in Religion should not last
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97050:9"/>long. <hi>Then did they strictly prohibit the</hi> Protestants <hi>from Printing any thing unless Licensed by the Chancellor of the Kingdom.</hi> Themselves in the mean time Divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their own Slanderous Pamphlets, and dangerous Writings against the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Also Instructions were given to the Captains and Judges, that they should suffer no Meetings in Churches, except themselves were present;</hi> And except they had a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Priest</hi> to Administer only in one kind.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Burgrave</hi> also who had the Custody of the Crown and Priviledges of the Kingdom, was Apprehended, because in the late Parliament he had stood for the free Election of a King, and delivered Prisoner to one of the bitterest Enemies of the Protestants.</p>
            <p>In other Places they destroyed the Churches of the Protestants.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of the year 1618. the Governors of the University and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistory met together, having formerly Power given them so to do; and choosing six persons, two Barons, two Knights, and two Citizens, to Consult what was best to be done in this time of their Enemies Insolency: There presently came an Injunction in <hi>Caesar</hi>'s Name to Inhibit them to call any together, and that if any man was called, he should not dare to appear upon the pain of High-Treason.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding which, the major part of the States met, and then new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions and Threats were spread abroad, and the States were informed that those Thunderbolts came not from the King, but from the Castle of <hi>Prague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon a great Tumult was raised in <hi>Prague,</hi> but the States Appeased it, and the first thing they did, was to banish the Jesuits out of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as the chief con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of these Mischiefs: Then did they write to <hi>Caesar,</hi> that they had no inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion against his Royal Majesty, but only to bring to punishment the Disturbers of publick Peace, being Authorized thereto by his Majestie's Letter, and bound by their Protestation; yet he resolved to revenge this Treason (as he called it) by Force of Arms, and the <hi>Bohemians</hi> on the other side resolved to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and for that end they chose Thirty Directors; and the <hi>Moravians</hi> and <hi>Silesians</hi> resolved to joyn with them, when they perceived Religion to be the Cause of the Quarrel. And indeed this was that which the <hi>Papists</hi> aimed at, and therefore they provoked the <hi>Bohemians</hi> by all ways, that so they might make a Conquest of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and for this end an <hi>Imperial</hi> Army presently entred the Kingdom under <hi>Dampier,</hi> and a <hi>Spanish</hi> Army under <hi>Buequay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time the States resolved not to admit <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to be their King, who was so open an Enemy both to their Religion and Liberties, and who was obtruded upon them without a due Election: They sent also Ambassadors to <hi>Franckford</hi> where the Electors were met together, to choose a new Emperor, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring that <hi>Ferdinand</hi> might not be admitted amonst them as King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding which he was admitted and chosen Emperor: The <hi>Bohemians</hi> in the mean time choosing <hi>Frederick</hi> Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> for their King; this more enraged their Enemies, so that they sent another Army under <hi>Maximilian</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> which took two <hi>Protestant</hi> Towns by Storm, and put all to the Sword, and every where made great Slaughter of the Protestants: Then the Imperial Armies came to <hi>Prague,</hi> which being strack with a Pannick fear, the Protestant Army being Overthrown in a set Battle under the Walls, and their new King fled, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up the City to them: The Conqueror promising to keep Articles agreed upon, but performing nothing less: For they did more mischief to the Protestant Religion by their Subtile and Slow Proceedings, than lately by their Outragious Fury; when the Sword, Fire and Wheel were the Instruments of their rage against the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97050:10"/>Protestants. For a little before when it was debated at <hi>Rome</hi> how they should deal with the <hi>Bohemians</hi> and <hi>Germans</hi> after the Conquest; it was agreed, that seeing their former strong purges which they had used to expel Haeretical Humours had not proved effectual; they therefore resolved not to put them to Death, wherein they did Glory as in Martyrdom; but rather to weary them, and change the hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surname of Inquisition into the mildel name of Reformation.</p>
            <p>And whereas there was a debate amongst the Imperialists at <hi>Prague,</hi> whether all the Protestants should be presently Banished, the Negative was resolved on, because they would then carry much away with them, and so Spoil the Province, and endure then Banishment with greater case, and therefore they concluded they must first besqueezed, and deprived of their Goods. And for this end the Souldiers at <hi>Prague</hi> were Authorized to Plunder the Houses of Noblemen and Citizens; yet this was done at several Seasons, and mostly in the Night, by which means, as the Enemies Boasted, they took from the Protestants some Millions of Gold: For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hither were all their Riches brought in the time of War, as to a place of the greatest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urity. But as this fell to the Commanders Shares, so the Neighbouring places were exposed to the Fury of the rest, the Common Souldiers Robbing and Spotling of Villages, Towns and Churches, Burning and Killing without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint: The Souldiers that were placed in Garrisons would not only have free Quarter, but extorted Money from their Landlords every day. Then were Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions sent at road promising Security to those Noblemen, Knights, Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Ministers that would bring in a good sum of Money to pay the Army, which yet they would not receive as a free gift, but only desired to borrow it. <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi>'s Protection was also promised to those that were Liberal, the rest were Threatned to be punished by the Souldiers.</p>
            <p>They set down also what Sums they expected from every one within such a time; they promised also that when that was paid, the Souldiers should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, which made every one to bring in their Plate, Money and Jewels the more willingly. Then were Commissioners sent to require certain Cities, that belonged to Protestant Noblemen to maintain the standing Forces of the Kingdom, and to contribute Corn for their publick Granaries: But whilst they were fed with a vain hope of lessening and removing the Souldiers, there were more Listed, which raised the Taxes so high as was impossible for the people to pay. And whereas some were allured to deny the Truth and turn <hi>Papists,</hi> that they might be cased of Taxes and Quarterings of Souldiers: This was not performed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they complained that Promise was broken with them. But the <hi>Jesuites</hi> Answered them, That they had no cause to complain, for they had provided for their Souls; and therefore they ought cheerfully to help the King by Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions and Quarterings of Souldiers; and that Hereticks must be dealt with as Mad-men and Children: From whom if you desire to get a Knife, you must shew them something else, though you never intend to give it them.</p>
            <p>Thus the Kingdom being emptied of Gold and Silver, Counterfeit and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Money was Coined in great abundance, that so the Common people might rejoyce in their Plenty; but in the mean time the Souldiers would receive none but good Money.</p>
            <p>Gold and Silver also was raised to Ten times the Price of it, and on a sudden the Emperor Diminished the value, making every piece of Money to be worth but the Tenth part; whereby the <hi>Bohemians</hi> were more Impoverished sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, than if they had lain under the burthen of an Army for Ten years.</p>
            <p>Then was it ordered that the Creditor should lose all the Money that he had Lent in the time of the Rebellion, as they called it. And thus they were first
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97050:10"/>Impoverished, after which the <hi>Papists</hi> Insulted over them by Infamous Books, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solent Pictures, and Proud words.</p>
            <p>Then did they send abroad their Commissioners for Reformation, who in every Town and Village endeavoured to bring Protestantise into Disgrace, and highly to magnifie and set abroad their own Cause. The most Eminention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for Honour and Estates were Invited to Apostacy, the Inferion sort are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fooled by there examples, or compelled by Threatnings. Then was there a High Court of Reformers set up, from which there was no Appeal.</p>
            <p>In the next place the Soulders exercised Barbarous Tyranny against the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Jesus Christ; one Aged Minister lying S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ek in his Bed, they Shot him to death as he lay: The next day they Robbed and Murthored another: Another, as he was Preaching to his people, they came into the Church and Shot him to Death. A Nobleman and a Minister hearing of Souldiers that were coming that way, conveyed themselves away into a place of Safety. The Souldiers when they came caught a School-Master, and Binding him in Cords, examined him where the Lord of that place, and the Minister were, and where they had hid their Treasure; he professed he knew neither the one nor the other. Whereupon they Beat him first with then Fists, then with Cudgels, then Stripping him Naked, they so extreamly Singed him with Fire, that at last he promised to bring them where the Treasure was, shewing them a Ditch full of Stones, which for Greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Gold they Emptied, but finding nothing, they Beat him Afresh; and when he professed he knew no Treasure, though through Pain he had said so much, they Cudgelled him, and with Clods Beat him into the Ditch, and Buried him under the Stones.</p>
            <p>Presently after they lighted on another Godly Minister, whom they so mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably Tortured, that he Died within five days, Shamefully abusing his Daughters also, whom they led away with them.</p>
            <p>Another Godly Minister, for a Month together they Exeruciated with new invented Mockeries: They Spit in his Face, Buffeted him with their Fists, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed him to be Beaten by every Vile Rascak; they with a Knotty Cord Twisted about his Forehead, with a Stick so strained his Head, that his very Eyes were ready to Start out: Then they let loose a Wild Horse upon him, which yet leaped quite over him, and did him no harm. At last, with much adoe he redeemed himself with five Hundred Florences.</p>
            <p>Another Minister they lighted on, and because he had a better Estate than the former, they Tormented him more; sometimes covering him over with not Burning Coals, sometimes with Ice, till they had forced him to pay a Thousand five Hundred Florences for his Ransome, though shortly after through Extremity of the pains he Died.</p>
            <p>Another Minister they fetched from his House, and miserably Tortured him, by Twisting a Cord about his Head; then tyed his Hands behind him, and his Legs with a small Cord, intending the next Morning to Torture him with File. But in the Night time, (as he was earnest at his Prayers; repeating these words, <hi>In thee, O Lord! is my Trust,</hi>) he perceived his Hands and Feet to be Miraculously loosned: Whereupon getting up, he went to the Gate, where were three Watchmen, one of them standing with his Hand on his Sword, yet he passed by them Undisco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; when he came to the Town-Gate, he was known by the Souldier that stood Sentinel, but he, being a <hi>Bohemian,</hi> was overcome by Intreaty, and let him pass over the Bridge, whereby he Escaped.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97050:11"/>
            <p> Another Minister with his Wife they Cruelly Burnt.</p>
            <p>Another was hanged upon a Cross-Beam, and making a Fire under him, they Broiled him to death: Another they cut in Small Pieces: Another Minister they soughts<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, but he being escaped, they took a Young man in his House, laid him on his back, filled his Mouth with Gunpowder, which setting Fire to, they miserably Tore his Jaws in pieces, and then Killed him.</p>
            <p>When Souldiers came to the House of another, he entertained them Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and made good Provision for them; but when they knew he was a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, they first Beat him Cruelly, then Killed him, stripped him, and plundered his House; they also Burnt his Library, and would not suffer his Body to buried for seven Weeks during their abode there.</p>
            <p>Another Aged Minister and his Wife were so sorely Burned by a Souldier that de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>anded Money of them, that presently after they Died.</p>
            <p>Another was Hung up by the Privy Members, being Seventy years Old, and his own Books Burnt under him, and at last was Shot through and Slain.</p>
            <p>Another was first Assessed at Seven Hundred Florences, and then had his House Plundered; and lastly, himself was Murthered.</p>
            <p>Another they caught and Wounded, Cutting his Neck half through; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards carried by some Friends to a Chirurgion, he Lived about two years, but in much pain and torment.</p>
            <p>Another being about Seventy years Old, they carried him into the Market place, where laying him upon a Fire they Burnt him to Death.</p>
            <p>Another was Beaten, so that he Died three days after.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jesuits</hi> laid wait for one <hi>Pessinus,</hi> a man Eminent for Learning and Piety, at last they Suborned an Apostate to betray him; who at last discovering him at he rode in a Coach with a Nobleman, Fourty Horsemen came suddenly and took him away: But by the Importunity of some Noblemen, he was Ransomed for four Thousand Florences, and ended his Life in Banishment. Another being bound to a Tree, was made a mark for the Musquetiers to Shoot at.</p>
            <p>Another being met by a notable <hi>Papist,</hi> was run through with a Spear; but all this was done through Military Licentiousness: Now we come to what was acted by Process of Law.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Anno <hi>1625.</hi> Six Articles were Exhibited to the <hi>Protestant</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations in <hi>Prague.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>THat they should lend some Thousands of Pounds to</hi> Caesar, <hi>for the payment of his Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>That they should publickly Renounce the coming in of</hi> Frederick.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>That they should bring into the Church the</hi> Popish <hi>Rites and Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97050:11"/> IV. <hi>That their Ministers should be ordained a new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>That the Ministers should leave their Wives, or get a Dispensation from the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>That such as would renounce their Ecclesiastical Functions, should have publick Promotions, and the Favour of</hi> Caesar.</p>
            <p>Then came forth an Edict, wherein the blame of all the former Rebellion (as they called it) was laid upon the Ministers of <hi>Prague,</hi> because they stirred up by their Lying Sermons (as they pleased to stile them) and by their Writings; not only the common people, but the Nobles also against <hi>Caesar;</hi> and that they were Authors of the choice of <hi>Frederick,</hi> and that they still laboured to stir up in the people a hatred against <hi>Caesar.</hi> Thereupon all the Ministers within <hi>Prague</hi> were required within three days to depart out of <hi>Prague,</hi> and within eight days to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the Kingdom, and the Provinces belonging thereto, and never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again: and if any by what pretence soever, should stay, or return again, or if any should presume to harbour or conceal any of them, that both the one and the other should suffer death, this was <hi>Anno</hi> 1621.</p>
            <p>Then were their Churches in <hi>Prague</hi> given to the <hi>Jesuits;</hi> it cannot be expressed what Lamentations and Mournings there were amongst the people, when thus they must leave their Pastors, and that for ever. Yet the <hi>German</hi> Ministers, whereof there were two, were suffered to continue in favour of the Duke of <hi>Saxony:</hi> then did as many as understood <hi>Dutch,</hi> stock to their Congregations, which so vexed the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> that they obtained not a Banishment, but a Gracious Dismission of them as they would have it called. Multitudes of people followed them, with great Lamentations and Tears, and in the Field they heard their Farewel Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>The next design was to remove the Ministers out of other free Cities, and the Commissioners of Reformation were imployed herein, one of them with a Troop of Horse coming to <hi>Slana,</hi> and going to Church, the Minister (a Godly and Learned man) was Reading the Gospel; the Commissioner sent a Souldier to him to bid him give over, but the Minister still going on, himself went to him with his Sword drawn crying out, <hi>Thou Foolish Preacher leave off thy Babling;</hi> and withall, he dashed the Bible out of his hand with his Sword. The Minister with Eyes, Hands, and Voice lift up to Heaven, repeated often, <hi>Wo, wo, unto you, you enter not into Heaven your selves, and forbid them that would. Wo, wo, wo unto you;</hi> but they mocking at these words, presently laid hands on him, lostling him to and fro; whereupon he said, <hi>I for the Name of my Lord Jesus Christ am ready to suffer all this, and what else you shall impose.</hi> The people were much Affrighted, but the chief Magistrates and many good Women interceeding for him, he was at last dismissed, provided that he should depart the City within three days.</p>
            <p>In a neighbouring City, the Minister for fear of these Barbarous Proceedings, went away of himself, yet the Commissioners extorted a great sum of Money from his Church, and Banished him in his Absence. In another place they commanded the Minister to depart from his Parish within three days, and from the City within eight days. He modestly asking the reason of his Banishment, they told him, Caesar <hi>by Conquest was Master of all the Churches, and that therefore he would put into them whom he pleased.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the Rooms of these Godly Preachers, were put in Unclean Men, Wicked Blasphemers, and Men illiterate, and of no worth, and yet they could not provide for all places; so that one of their Hirelings supplyed divers Churches, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97050:12"/>instead of the wholesome Food of God's word, he sed them with Poison. Then brought they ignorant Monks out of <hi>Poland,</hi> unprofitable Burthens to the Earth, yet fit enough to be promoters of an Ignorant and Antichristian Religion.</p>
            <p>Also a Commissioner, with some Troops of Horse, entring into <hi>Guttenburgh,</hi> a place Famous for maintaining the Orthodox Faith, calls before him the Ministers, casts them out of their places, and puts <hi>Jesuits</hi> into their Churches: And these <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits</hi> urging it, the Ministers were commanded to depart out of the City Gates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore break of day, and out of the Kingdom within eight days. Hereby were twenty one Ministers driven away, many Citizens accompanying them; one of them at the parting preached upon that Text, <hi>They shall cast you out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues,</hi> exhorting them to perseverance. All the multitude much bewailed their loss, and with great Lamentations, Walling and Kissing each other, they recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended themselves to the Blessing and Protection of the Almighty.</p>
            <p>In every place the Ministers were cast out of their Livings, some Imprisoned, and after a while dismissed; and all commanded to depart the Kingdom upon pain of Death. Some were strifled with Stinks whilst they lay in Prison.</p>
            <p>At last <hi>Anno</hi> 1624 another Decree came forth from the King, whereby all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Ministers were commanded to depart the Kingdom by a peremptory day prefixed; because, as was alleadged, they were Seditious men, and Seducers of the people: Yet herein they used this Artifice, that in most places this Edict was concealed, till the time was almost or altogether elapsed; so that by this means the Ministers not having time to communicate their Councels together, went into several Provinces; and some were fain to hide themselves in Caves and Dens, and those either returned privately and Visited their Auditors, or comforted such as came to them in the Mountains and Woods, Preaching and Administring the Sacraments unto them.</p>
            <p>But as soon as the Enemies understood it, they presently published a new Decree, wherein a punishment was proposed to those that should conceal the Ministers, and a reward to such as should betray them. Whereupon some of the Ministers were taken and cast into Prison; then by the <hi>Jesuits</hi> were they by all ways Sollicited to Apostacy: And fear of Death, Hunger, Cold, the Stinck of the Prison, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with some to renounce their Ministry. But most bore up Couragiously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Storms; and at last some by paying great Sums, others by giving it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Hands, that they would never return in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> were dismissed.</p>
            <p>One Godly Minister was examined by Tortures, when, where, and to whom he had Administred the Sacraments of Baptism, or the Lords Supper: He An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, <hi>That he had neither laid down, nor slacked his Ministry, which he had received from Christ, and not from</hi> Caesar. Being profered Life if he would change his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, he Answered, <hi>This Body of mine is subject to Corruption, and now it begins to decay already; why would you have me hinder it?</hi> Being brought forth to Execution, the Cryer with a loud voice proclaimed, <hi>That he was guilty of Sedition:</hi> But he with a loud voice laid, <hi>I suffer for the Truth of Christ.</hi> None of the Citizens were suffered to accompany him; yea, they were▪ Threatned to be Shot, if they did but look out at their Windows: And that his voice might not be heard, the Drums and Trumpets Sounding continually as he was passing on, he cheerfully said, <hi>This day shall my Soul be with Christ;</hi> the Captain said, <hi>With the Devil in Hell:</hi> The Martyr replyed, <hi>But you with your impious Crew will run headlong thither, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye Repent.</hi> Then was his Right Hand cut off, wherewith he gave the Cup in the Sacrament; then was his Head cut off, his Bowels taken forth and wraped in his Shirt, his Quarters set upon four Stakes, and his Head upon the fifth.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97050:12"/>
            <p> After this did the Commissioners go into <hi>Moravia</hi> to a Noble Baron, called <hi>Charles de Zerotina,</hi> a man for Wisdom, Vertue Famous through all <hi>Europe,</hi> and a constant Professor of Religion; and one who maintained Twenty four Ministers of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion within his Jurisdiction: They told him, <hi>That they had an express Command from Cardinal</hi> Ditrichstaine, <hi>to expel all those Ministers out of the Country.</hi> He Answered, <hi>That in matters of Religion he ought not to be subject to the Cardinal, and therefore from him he Appeals to</hi> Caesar. They granted him Fourteen days to prosecute his Appeal, but the Baron being not in Health, could not go in that time to <hi>Caesar.</hi> Then they came again to him, and told him, <hi>That it should be in his choice, whether he would send them away himself, or suffer them to do it:</hi> The Baron Answered, <hi>That he would not Banish those whom he knew to be the Servants of Christ, nor could consent that they should do it.</hi> Yet that Night they sent abroad their Citations, to require all the Inhabitants of that Village, to appear before them the next Morning; at which time the Minister and People came: Then did they read to them <hi>Caesar's</hi> Edict, asking them if they would submit to it; they Answered, <hi>That they wholly relyed upon the will of God, whom they served in the Gospel of his Son; and therefore they resolved to undergo what punishment they should Inflict, seeing they suffered only for the Name of Jesus Christ, and not for any ill Deeds.</hi> Then they demanded of them whether they would forsake their Heresie, and turn to the Catholick Church, which they unanimously denyed. The Commissioners would have given them time to consider of it, but they all Answered: <hi>That in so Religious a cause as this, they needed no deliberations.</hi> Hereupon in <hi>Caesar's</hi> Name they Banished them, commanding them to depart within eight days. These Godly persons obeyed, and by the Baron, at his own charge they were conveyed into <hi>Hungary.</hi> The like they did in other places, so that the Ministers of the Gospel through all <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Moravia,</hi> were thrust out, and Ignorant and Illiterate persons were put in their Rooms.</p>
            <p>The next Design of the Enemies was against the Nobles, the Crime was for taking up Arms for <hi>Frederick</hi> their Lawful King, against an Usurper: For though hope of Pardon was granted, if laying down Arms they would submit to <hi>Caesar's</hi> Mercy, yet divers of them were apprehended, and first they seised upon some that were of the Rank of Defenders of the Kingdoms Liberties. And this was all the Mercy and Clemency that <hi>Protestants</hi> enjoyed under the Reign of <hi>Popish Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>